OK, I guess it's time to get started.
This sounds a bit weird.
Is it OK?
Can people hear me in the back?
OK, I don't know why it sounded weird, but it's good that say it again.
See, maybe it sounds a bit loud, but OK, let's see.
So reduce the how about now, Is it better?
OK, let's find both ways.
OK, Depends on the sensitivity of the input device that you guys have.
You know, my input device may be a bit more sensitive.
I don't know.
Or less, depending on the situation.
OK, it's good to see you all here.
Looks like this is the fraction of people who decided not to go on an early break.
Is that true?
OK, since you'll have a long break soon, starting tomorrow.
Tomorrow.
We don't have lecture, as you know.
So today we're going to cover precise exceptions and interrupts.
You covered a lot when I was at a conference last week.
You covered how to design the micro architecture, basically principles, single cycle micro
architectures, multi cycle micro architectures.
Today we're going to talk about pipelining and today we're going to talk about how to make
pipelining essentially work using precise exceptions and interrupts.
And building on this next week, not next week, but after the break, we're going to start out of
order execution, which is really how to execute instructions out of their original program order,
which is going to build on this lecture because this lecture is going to build the foundations of
what we need for out of order execution engines.
So this lecture is really important actually for multiple reasons.
1 is how do we enable a machine to be more easily debugable and also communicate with outside
devices and also higher performance while preserving the sequential semantics.
OK, so I hope you guys are excited to learn about precise exceptions and interrupts.
Has anybody learned about these before?
OK, in what?
Lecture at another university?
OK, yeah, doesn't count, but it's good.
Hopefully maybe you can ask questions.
OK, so this is what I said prior to last week and last week.
Well, today, today, we're actually still covering pipelining, but really transitioning from
pipelining to out of order execution.
As you will see, I don't intend to get out of order execution today.
If you have time, I will cover some other things than reorder buffer, but let's see how it goes.
And these are your readings.
You have some readings about out of order execution going into the future.
And this nice paper by Smith and Sohey covers the micro architecture of superscalar and out of order
processors.
So you can take a look at this.
There is no good book, let's say that covers that, at least in the detail that we want.
So that paper would be a good reading material if you're interested, but I'm going to give a
different perspective.
So basically this lecture is about preserving sequential semantics and sequential semantics is
dictated by the von Neumann model, right?
So in multi cycle execution, which is what we do when we have multi cycle processors or pipeline
processors, not all instructions take the same amount of time in the execute state of the pipeline.
And the idea, one idea is to have multiple functional units that take different number of cycles.
So we're extending the pipelining idea right now a little bit.
So your pipeline looks kind of like this.
Now you can have a fetch and a decode stage.
And then based on the type of the instruction, you have different types of execution or functional
units.
And these functional units may have may take different amounts of time, for example.
In addition, may take only one cycle and multiplication may take 4 cycles in this picture.
And a floating point multiplication, which is another data type that's much more expensive to
operate on may take 8 cycles and a load store may take 100 cycles, right?
And you can keep expanding this.
A matrix multiplication for example may take 100 cycles also.
Who knows.
So this could these execution units can be pipelined or not pipelined.
That's not that important here.
The key is they take different number of cycles from each other and we will run into a problem if
they do take a different number of cycles.
Basically this pipeline structure can start independent instructions in different functional units
before a previous long latency instruction finishes execution, right?
For example, you have a, you have AFP multiply instruction that goes here and then the next
instruction.
Doesn't need the result, so it goes to the integer multiply unit, assuming it's integer multiply,
and then the next instruction doesn't is independent of all of those, it could go to the integer
addition unit, for example.
So you can actually have multiple instructions concurrently executing because later instructions
don't need the data produced by the previous instructions.
And this enables higher throughput of course, and so it is a reasonable design to do.
And this is essentially the extended version of the pipelining that you saw before with a multiple
functional units.
It's a more reasonable type of pipeline, if you will, as opposed to having a single ALU for example.
OK, so the question is what happens at the end, right?
Well, not just what happens at the end, we're going to cover other issues, but also, but that's one
issue basically who writes its result to the register file first?
That's one of the thing key things that we're going to discuss today.
So basically, let's take a look at this example.
Instructions can take different number of cycles to execute in this execute stage.
For example, we're comparing here integer ads which take 4 cycles total, but in the execute stage
they take one cycle.
And then integer divide operations, which luckily take 8 cycles here, but they may take actually
much longer in real life because divide is a very expensive operation in general.
But my slide is not that long, so I I take 8 cycles over here.
So if you look at this program, you're executing a divide and an ads and then a bunch of other ads
and then another divide and then ads and then a bunch of other ads.
So assume that these are independent of each other.
If they're depend on each other, we're going to handle that later on.
Actually a little bit today, but really next week after the after the Easter break, that's going to
be important also.
But assume that these are independent right now.
And I give you this picture, this is a timeline.
In clock cycle one, this is fetched.
In clock cycle two, the first one is fetched, the second one is the first one is decoded, the second
one is fetched.
And you can see you're used to these timelines by now, right?
And if I ask you what is wrong with this picture in one moment architecture, what would you say,
anybody?
Or is everything good?
This is how we should be building our machines.
W is right back.
That's my hint for you.
The instruction writes back its results of the register file.
Anybody.
Otherwise, I'm going to answer going once, twice, Last chance that is wrong.
Basically, this instruction writes its result into R3 before the previous instruction writes its
result into R4.
Remember, it's von Neumann architecture says we have a sequential execution model.
An instruction should finish before the next instruction starts.
Right now, forget about writing its result into the register file before the next instruction
starts.
Here, we start things.
We violate things because we pipeline things, but we violate things even worse because now the
result is visible to someone.
It's in the register file.
If someone goes and inspects that register file, they will see some out of order execution
happening.
Whereas von Neumann said everything should be sequential, right?
So there are other things that are wrong.
This is wrong also.
This is wrong also because all those results are written to the register file before the previous
execution, before the previous divide wrote its result.
And this is wrong also.
Yes.
Will the first divide instructions even be correctly stored to R4?
Or will this be written because took over and so now there are four and it's lost?
So, yeah, well, it's, it's assuming it's correct.
They executed R4.
These are writing to different registers, like completely independent basically.
So the other instruction should not affect R4.
Well, if you design things correctly, no, it should not.
So we're assuming that you design things correctly so that they don't overtake.
There are no dependencies.
OK, OK.
So basically you should not write results to the architectural state out of order.
That's what we're violating here.
You can say, why is this important?
Everything is independent of each other over here.
If you go into dependencies, things become even more messy.
But this is important because, well, I, that's basically, I said sequential semantics is not
preserved.
Basically, we're breaking a huge principle here.
That's why it's important.
And whenever you break a principle, you run into problems.
Meaning, I thought you were going to ask this question actually, which is, what if Dwight actually
doesn't finish because there's a problem with the Dwight, right?
What if it incurs an exception?
Meaning divide is not possible to execute by the machine for whatever reason.
For example, divide by zero and the machine determines that R2 is 0 and it throws an exception.
This is an unknown number right?
Now, what do you do?
Right?
You've written some results.
That you're not supposed to write based on the sequential semantics and this divide through an
exception and someone needs to handle it.
How many people dealt with exceptions in programs?
Yeah.
How many people wrote try catch blocks, for example, in Java, Right.
This is that sort of thing.
You're trying to do something, an instruction at the lower level, of course, right?
At the programming language level, you try to do something and if there's some problem, you throw an
exception, right?
And that gets implemented with what we're going to discuss actually later in this lecture.
So it's the same thing that's happening at a lower level.
You should not have written to that register because, OK, if this, this divide threw an exception,
that means something is wrong with the program.
The programmer may want to inspect what's going on, right?
And you should allow the programmer to inspect in a way that they can debug their program, right?
And if things are written out of order, the programmer has no idea what may have happened because
that depends on the micro architectural state right now of the program.
That's why preserving A precise state is going to be very important.
I'm going to get back to that again.
Basically, this is an exception causing instruction, and it basically should stop at that point.
No other instruction should have retired or finished or updated the architectural state, and all
previous instructions should have completed.
Also, even though I didn't show anything over there, all previous instructions should have completed
so that the programmer has a clean slate, clean point.
So this happens not just with an exception, but how many people have debug programs?
A lot of you.
How many people have set break points in a debugger?
Same thing.
When you set a break point, you're really causing an exception with that instruction.
You set a break point at a particular point in a program that gets associated with a particular
instruction and that instruction calls an exception in hardware so that you can inspect the state.
And the state that you expect when you set a break point is the sequential execution state.
If it's not sequential, if these other instructions that come after the break point, let's say you
set the break point at that device, have updated the architectural state, you will go crazy because
you don't know which instructions have written you.
You have, you know exactly what should have happened if the instructions executed in the sequential
order, right?
But if something happens underneath some other instructions complete, you don't expect that, right?
OK, this problem becomes worse as we will see with all of order execution later on.
OK, this is my one of my favourite exceptions.
So you guys probably have taken trams at some point in your lives.
This tram had an exception.
It shouldn't have stopped over there, but you can see the timeline also at 12:55.
It had an exception.
It's an exception causing instruction and this other instruction gets delayed due to that exception
basically, right?
And there are other instructions that get delayed.
And you can see that this is stopped in a weird place.
As you can see, that's why it's exceptional, right?
So, OK, so time goes on.
I keep walking good that I didn't wait.
And you can see the exception causing instruction over there still causing the exception.
So it gets delayed at some point, exception gets handled and resolved and the exception causing
instruction continues.
Now you see what happened, Somebody fixed that exception causing instruction, right?
It could be.
And we're going to see how things may be fixed over here.
If you set a break point, for example, you go to an exception routine where the programmer can
inspect things and then eventually return to the next instruction, right?
You actually execute the instruction, go to the next instruction.
If it is divide by zero, you go to a routine that says handle divide by zero.
Programmer can supply that.
For example, programmer says if get it, if I get a zero in the divide by zero, I'm going to replace
it with one or whatever, right?
You can actually patch the program in some way, right?
You can actually do a lot of these tricks in with exceptions.
OK, so I, I would like to distinguish between exceptions and interrupts.
Unfortunately, not all IS as distinguish between these nicely, but they're fundamentally different
things.
So so far I talked about exception causing instruction.
Exception is something internal to the running program, right?
That's that tram that's going, right?
If something was external, that's interrupt.
For example, if someone goes in front of the tram and the tram decides to stop, that would be good,
good actually.
Then that's an interrupt.
Basically, the tram's execution is interrupted at some point, right?
It's similar in terms of what happens.
Probably the resolutions may be different, but basically these are two different things, internal
versus external, but they're both unplanned changes or interruptions in program execution.
So exceptions are due to internal problems in the execution of the program.
We're going to call these exceptions, and if they're due to external events that need to be handled
by the processor, they're interrupts.
For example, an external event, maybe somebody's inputting.
Something into the keyboard, right?
And that is actually I could actually interrupt the processor.
The processor may actually pull what's happening.
The processor may actually go into a state, stop executing the existing programme, go into a state
where actually it figures out what people what that person inputs, right, That's an interrupt.
Another interrupt is power failure.
For example, the power is not enough, so the program gets interrupted and the system and the
processor takes some action to handle power failure, right?
Low battery, for example, could be an interrupt.
Also, these external events are interrupts, but both of them in the end require stopping the current
program.
Assuming various if you have a single processor at this point, if you have multiple processors,
interrupts can be handled in some other processor actually.
So that's a one another difference over here because it's internal versus external, right?
But assume that you have a single processor which we've assumed so far.
You stop the current program, you save the architectural state and hopefully you guys remember what
architectural state is.
Program counter registers memory and you handle the exception interrupt by switching to some
software which is part of the operating system called the exception or interrupt handler.
And if possible and makes sense, you return back to program execution.
This depends on the nature of the exception.
If it's divide by zero and and the programmer doesn't supply anything, basically halt the program,
right?
The program in so you don't go back.
If if for example, you have a null pointer dereference that causes an X axis protection exception
again, if the system didn't get supplied with a handler that does something special, in that case
you don't go back to the program, right?
So it really depends.
That's why this is if it if it's possible and it makes sense.
OK, let's take a look at some of these examples.
I've given you some, but exception can be divide by zero, overflow, undefined instruction, undefined
op code.
You may actually, the program counter may point to some values that are not OP codes, right?
For whatever reason, maybe there's a bug in your program, maybe somebody corrupt your memory, who
knows, right?
It's, it's going to happen.
General protection or access protection page faults, which we will see in Lecture 25 and Lecture 26
when we talk about virtual memory.
These are all exceptions that are internal to the program interrupt examples.
IO device may need service.
There may be system timer.
For example, periodically system may actually want to do something.
This operating system actually does that for maintenance functions of the system.
It may basically interrupt the program, Kick It Out and do some maintenance and then bring it back.
Decide which program to schedule.
For example, operating systems usually have timers to decide, oh, this program is executed enough,
now it's time for the other program to execute fairness.
For example, how do you do fair scheduling across different programs?
Or this program is interacting with the user right now, so it should be scheduled right away, right?
There could be power failure, machine check, machine check is usually some exceptional condition
where you actually get an error, for example, in the machine, in some part of the machine.
So you interrupt the running program because it's not safe for the running program to continue
executing because the memory detect an error, for example.
Then the program machine goes into a state where you try to figure out what the error is.
Can it, can you correct it?
Does it, does it affect the existing program?
Etcetera.
Right.
So these are all external to the program as you can see, right.
OK.
A little bit more about the exceptions where syntrops cause is clearly difference between them
internal versus external.
We've handle, we've harped on that when to handle them because of the cause, because of the
difference in cause when to handle them actually varies also.
So exceptions, you need to handle them when they're detected.
And if the exception is known to be non speculative, you talked about branch prediction, for
example, there may be some speculative exceptions that are not at the head of the instruction are
not due to all this instruction in the machine yet.
So you don't want to handle the instruction that may have caused an exception in the fetch stage
because that instruction may be flushed, right?
You really want to handle when you detect the exception and you, you know that it's non speculative
basically almost immediately, right?
Interrupts can on the other hand can be handled when there, when it's convenient for the machine.
Because for example, if the interrupt is due to an IO device needing some service, there's some
slack IO device can wait it for a long time, maybe it can wait a little bit more, right?
Or if it's a system timer expiration, you don't need to be perfectly exact in in terms of nanosecond
level.
So you can wait a little bit, you can actually finish the program in a nice state and then handle
things.
Whereas power failure may, you may not need it, you may not want to wait basically.
So when convenient, except for very high priority ones like power failure or machine check, these
are really high priority interrupts.
They kick out the program that's running.
In the processor so that the system can take action regarding power failure, like to save the state
somewhere so that you can restart things in a much better way.
There's also the priority concept of priority.
I will not go into this a lot of detail, but everything in the system has a priority and the
priority of when to the exception is depend on the process because it's internal to the process.
Whereas priority of the interrupt depends on the type of the interrupt.
Essentially, right, Because exception is internal.
Everything related to the exception is really related to the process or the program that's running
OK, handling context.
It's essentially related to priority.
I'm not going to talk about that, but essentially who handles things?
Exception is handled based on the context of the process.
So the programmer can actually affect this, whereas interrupted handle based on the system.
So there's a system programmer that wrote how to handle the interrupt that comes from a device, for
example, a microphone, for example, or something else that comes outside, right?
OK, interrupts are actually really important.
Like if you have systems that are interacting with the environment, they're actually taking in a lot
of inputs, right?
And they could be processed using interrupts essentially.
So interrupts, interrupt handling, how quickly you actually handle those interrupts so that you can
communicate with the world is becoming much, much more important with robotics, cyber, physical
systems, etcetera.
So it's good to think about this going into the future.
Some of the system design decisions are not necessarily designed for handling these things fast.
OK.
So OK, any questions so far?
We're going to talk about architectural state a lot.
That's why I put this architectural state again over here.
This is based on your prior lectures.
Essentially, architectural state is memory registers and program counter, right?
And instructions specify how to transform the values of this architectural or programmer visible
state.
And you've seen how to implement instructions in very different ways so far.
So what does precise mean?
That's the title of this lecture, right?
So precise exceptions or interrupts means that the architectural state should be consistent or
precise when the exception or interrupt is ready to be handled.
Essentially, there's a concept in von Neumann model doesn't exist in data flow model.
It's good to think about that later on, but it's a concept and one moment model because 1 moment a
model has a sequential execution paradigm.
You need to make sure that all.
So basically to ensure a precise state, you need to ensure 2 things.
All previous instructions should be completely retired for before the exception causing instruction
or before the instruction at which point you want to handle an interrupt that's coming in and no
later instruction should be retired, meaning no later instruction should have updated the
architectural state.
Architectural state includes PC program, counter, memory registers, right?
That's it basically.
Basically retire means commit, finish, execution and update architectural state if you don't
remember.
So if the divide calls an exception, this is the the precise state basically.
Or in this particular case, I guess I just show it an example precise state.
If the white caused an exception, the line should be actually higher.
But in this case, maybe add caused an exception or something else happens in between, right?
So basically this is an example of a precise state.
It's a clean separation of sequential instruction.
It could be anywhere, but you'd better have it when you cause the exception.
All previous instructions are retired.
All instructions after that did not retire.
OK, that's the idea.
The question is how do we actually support this, right.
It's easier said than done.
If you start, if you start doing multi cycle execution, supporting this becomes not so easy and we
will see ways of supporting it.
Sounds good.
OK, so before we go into supporting it, at least the structure that I'm going to introduce, let's
talk a little bit about what you do when you actually handle exceptions in pipeline.
When do you check for this?
Essentially, as I said, you don't want to handle exceptions speculatively, meaning before you know
that you have to handle them.
So when the oldest instruction is ready to be retired, you check whether it have it has caused an
exception.
When the oldest, for example the divide instruction, you check whether there's an exception.
And hardware actually has signals related to this.
We will see that you know that there should there could be a divide by zero signal, for example,
right?
And once the if it's detected that it has caused some exception, what the the control logic needs to
take some actions first.
It ensures architectural state is precise.
Hopefully you built that control logic to be that way.
It flushes and then you need to handle, you need to prepare the machine for the exception handling
routine to come and execute, right?
What does that mean?
That means existing program should not continue to run, right?
Because it's caused an exception.
Something needs to happen, right?
So what do you?
Do with the remaining instructions that come after the exception causing instruction, you flush the
pipeline, you get rid of them because you don't need them anyway, right?
You need to handle the exception, they're useless for you.
You save, meaning the control logic that handles the exception saves the program counter and the
registers as specified by the ISA and all IS as have ways of specifying things as to what needs to
be saved, where should it be saved, etcetera.
We're not going to go into that, but I'm going to give you some examples from MIPS, for example.
And this control logic redirects the fetch engine, meaning the program counter to the appropriate
exception handling routine.
So a program counter is changed to some address where the exception handling routine starts.
And that exception handling routine determines what kind of exception is it.
It is.
And then it determines what else needs to be done to handle that exception.
Makes sense, right?
And that exception handling routine at some point can say, oh, I cleaned up the exception so I can
now go back to the program that was executing.
And how does it know how to go back?
Because this control logic saved the program counter of the exception causing instruction and also
the register state of the program that caused the exception.
So all of those get loaded back to the processor by the exception handling routine using some
special instructions, and then you can go back to executing the program.
It's not as if nothing happened, but essentially something got interrupted in between exception
handling between got executed and then you go back to the program.
Makes sense, right?
So that's how you service an exception.
Interrupts are essentially the same, except they're caused externally, not internally.
Sounds good, right?
OK, so this is X86 actually is one of the in my opinion, it's one of the most complex IS as, but
it's one of the beautiful IS as that gets a lot of things right in terms of description.
Some IS as I say, they don't even they say they call everything interrupts, which is a bit odd to
me, but X86 gets it gets it nice.
So here, for example, I'm going to read this.
You can read the rest over here.
When an interrupt is received or an exception is detected, the currently running procedure or task
is suspended while the processor executes an interrupt or exception handler.
When the execute, when execution of the handler is complete, the processor resumes execution of the
interrupted procedure or task.
The resumption of the uninterrupt interrupted procedure or task happens without loss of program
continuity unless recovery from an exception was not possible or an interrupt caused the currently
earning program to be terminated.
So this is a nice summary of what happens at a very high level.
The question is how do you support this?
And we're going to talk about that, but ISA manuals are very nice to read.
OK, so before we go into how do we support that, I want to actually talk about this.
Why do we want precise exceptions a little bit more because this is actually quite important.
And if you remember the data flow lecture, I said that one of the beauties of the von Neumann
machine is you know exactly what your state is.
Whereas data flow, it's very difficult to have this precise state.
Where do you do over the precise line?
Program counter doesn't exist in data flow, right?
So this is one of the difficulties of building a data flow machine.
So first of all, because the semantics of the von Neumann model ISA specifies it, you got to obey
it, that's for sure.
Yes, True.
Otherwise you're violating the contract.
And as a result, somebody may not be able to write a program.
That's correct, Right.
OK.
The other reason is even if I say it was not von Neumann, for some reason, let's say software
debugging.
Basically, if you want to debug software that you wrote, you have some bugging your program, you're
trying to figure out what's going on.
You basically set breakpoints.
For example, you need to go line by line or some in some in some way.
You will need to understand how state transitions happen.
And you need to make sense of those state transitions such that you can say after this state I
should have this value.
After the state I should have this value, right?
If you have precise exceptions, you can clearly identify a point at which you can reason about the
state.
This, these are my, these are my, these should be my register values at this point in time, assuming
everything is correct in the program.
This is how you can debug the program, right?
Even if you don't have the sequential model for whatever reason.
Think about it, right?
And this software debugging is very difficult if some values get updated in a manner where you
cannot reason about state transitions, right?
So of course, sequential execution makes the state transitions much nicer.
You know that everything previous to this instruction that caused the that you're trying to debug at
the point at that point of the instruction has retired and nothing else has retired.
So you know exactly what the state should be at that point.
And this makes debugging really, really easy.
OK, if you don't believe this, try debugging something where a lot of values get updated in an out
of order manner and you're going to see out of order execution.
It's very difficult.
In fact, people have tried IBM, for example, the first, one of the first most popular out of order
execution machines that we're going to study after, after the break, Thomas Saul's machine, IBM
36091.
It did not support precise exceptions.
It was, it was one of the most powerful machines of its time, supercomputer of its time in 1960s.
We're talking about it.
It did not support precise exceptions and as a result, nobody wanted to use it, nobody except for a
few people who who could basically sit down and debug their programs in the presence of this out of
order updates.
Yeah.
So software debugging is probably the most important reason why we want precise exceptions.
Now, if you don't have precise exceptions, you can still debug your programs, but you got to be at a
level where you can reason about a lot of things.
And you may go crazy while doing that.
And we know that most of the world is not going to debug programs that way, right?
OK, OK.
The other benefit is enable the easy recovery from exceptions.
If the state is clear, you can go back to that state immediately.
You don't need to undo a lot of things.
For example, it enables easily restartable processes.
So if you actually have a clean state, you can easily restart the process by saying, I go back to
this program counter and here are the register values up there.
You just basically update those.
That's it.
And this is something that's important we didn't discuss at all, but it enables traps into software.
So this is actually nice.
For example, you did not implement.
Let's assume that you designed an ISA and you made a mistake, meaning or maybe you, you made it, you
made it, you made a design choice, let's say, not necessarily a mistake.
It could be a design choice or a mistake, depending on the frequency of the occurrence of the
instruction that you decided not to implement.
Right?
For example, you designed that ISA and you did not add a multiply instruction to your ISA.
OK, ISA does not have a multiply instruction, which was actually true for MIPS originally, And we're
going to talk about that also later on because that was a philosophy.
We don't want complicated instructions in the ISA.
We want to make the hardware simple.
OK, but you can still and but but people want multiply instructions from you and you cannot change
the hardware at this point.
So how do you add a multiply instruction into the programs?
One way of doing it is actually add the multiply instruction somehow into the programs.
And when that multiply instruction, when you get, when the, when the system gets to that multiply
instruction, it calls an exception, undefined opcode exception because the hardware doesn't have
that hardware calls an undefined opcode exception.
You go into the exception handler and this exception handler checks the value and quoted value.
Oh, there's a multiply instruction and somebody writes a multiply routine in software that uses the
instructions of the hardware that you already have, like shifts and adds to actually execute that
multiply instruction in software.
And then you go back to the program after that multiply instruction finishes, patch the register
file, etcetera.
So that's how you can actually implement a software defined opcode.
And when you heard hear about software defined opcode, that's what it is.
It is not.
I'm not going to say it's not possible, but it's not easily doable if you don't have precise
exceptions or interrupts because this requires again, your state to be clean, right?
Otherwise, you need to actually, you need to actually store a lot of States and maybe undo or redo
some execution while you're also doing the multiply, right?
So it's good to think about it.
So this precise exception concept enables a lot of things and this is one of them as we will see.
It also enables virtual memory, but I'm going to leave that to lecture 25 or 26.
OK?
Any questions?
OK, So this is another concept where the importance it it simplifies it, it complicates the hardware
a little bit, but it simplifies programmers life a lot easier to make it to make it a lot easier.
OK, so how do we ensure precise exceptions?
I'm going to cover some machines.
Essentially this is easy to do in single cycle and multi cycle machines, multi cycles a little bit
more, a little bit harder, but we will see that.
And your book section 7.7 has a nice treatment in multi cycle architect micro architecture.
I'm going to show in a single cycle machine that's not a problem because instruction boundary is
really the same as a cycle boundary.
An instruction is guaranteed to be finished in one cycle, so there's no possibility of violating
sequential execution semantics, right?
So if an instruction calls an exception, you handle it right away because you have a single cycle,
right?
And but we know that single cycle machines are not realistic, so I'm not going to harp on that.
Multi cycle machines.
Much more realistic, although low performance to support interrupts.
And exceptions.
We need to add special states in the control finite state machine.
And you've seen those finite state machines in the last lectures.
These states lead to exceptional or interrupt handlers.
I'm going to show you some states for undefined up code, for example, or for overflow.
Divide by zero is very similar actually.
And the finite state machine is designed such that you switch to the handler only at a precise
state, meaning before fetching the next instruction, right?
As long as you handle the exception or interrupt before fetching the next instruction, you're
guaranteeing that all previous instructions have retired and no later instruction has retired.
OK, so maybe I'll start with the finite state machine over here very quickly.
But this is a multi cycle finite state machine that we kind of developed actually in late last
lectures, MIPS version, but it's appended with some additional states over here.
For example, it supports overflow and undefined instruction.
So you amend the finite state machine with a state.
So this is an R type operation, which is which could be an AD for example.
Overflow means the value that you generate as a result of the operation cannot be represented with
number of bits that you have.
So you've overflown.
Basically, you increment the register value by 1 and then you cannot represent that value, right?
So if, and this needs to be detected by hardware, so hardware has a bit, says overflow, ALU has a
bit says overflow.
And if that overflow bit is set, the next state after executing the instruction is a special state
where you prepare the machine for exception handling.
We're going to see what those things are.
If there's no overflow, you basically write to the destination register, right?
Basically, you change the state machine such that if there's an exceptional condition, you don't
write to the destination register.
There's no Reg dest equal 1 over here, for example.
But you actually prepare some special registers in the machine such that you can jump to the
exception handler and we're going to see what those special register are.
For example, what is the, what is the cause of the interrupt or exception?
And you you also store the exception causing program counter, for example, in in the in the PC.
I'm going to show you the data path in a little bit.
This is another exception over here that's added at the finite state machine.
This is the decode stage.
You can see the decode stage based on this multi way jump in the finite state machine.
If the OP is not recognised, if the OP is not our type or this or this or this or this or this, it
must be undefined.
So you go to a state where you prepare the machine for a different cause exception with a different
cause, in this case undefined instruction, right?
And you change, you also store the exception causing program counter and you write to the program
counter such that you go to the right place in the exception handling.
OK.
And then you go back to the fetch state as you can see over here.
OK, so I'm going to get to this later on.
It's not as important, but basically you need to change the finite state machines such that you can
jump into different States and avoid.
Writing to the destination register when an exception happens, you also need to whenever you need to
add states to the data path, you may need to add clearly add states to finite state machine.
You may need to add circuitry in the data path also to support what you're trying to do, right.
So we're trying to handle the exceptions.
In this particular case, we add, for example, an EPC register that holds the exception causing PC
program counter, because we're going to store that somewhere there's a cause register that holds
the cause of the exception.
It could be in this particular case, only two things, but this could be actually 100 different
things, right?
In a real machine.
But you can see that it's another register over here, this EPC register, this is a cause register.
And then exception handler starts at some address specified by the MIPS ISA, and that particular
address is specified by the MIPS ISA.
And essentially you need to have a way of setting these registers, for example, and also jumping to
the exception handler.
For example, there's there's an overflow of signal over here that comes out of the ALU and that
signal is tested by the state.
Undefined instruction doesn't need a state because you're eliminating based on all the other
possibilities.
If the op OP code is something else, then you'd go into a different state.
So that's handled in the state machine and you can see that the control signals are whether you're
right to the exception causing program counter register, whether you're right to the cause of the
exception or interrupt.
And then there is a multiplexer that's added to decide what is the cause.
Basically there needs to be a value associated with each cause of exception or interrupt, as you can
see.
And then you'll need to change the data path such that you can jump to the exception handler, which
is the this address over here.
Here and there should be a path provided to update the program counter with that exception handler
routine, OK.
And you can see that if we detect an overflow, we set PC source to 11 and we set PC right such that
this value goes into the program counter, right?
So you go into the exception routine, Oh something happened and interrupt calls is set to 0 which
happens to be that encoding for overflow and you write the cause and you wrote the exception
causing program counter also.
OK, so this is the support, a minimal type of support that you add in a multi cycle machine.
There's also this MFC-0 instruction which has a terrible name.
I think it's move from Co processor 0 instruction they say.
So MIPS when it was designed it was thinking of this exception handling part as a Co processor that
helps the main processor.
That's why it's called move from Co processor zero.
There are other Co processors also Co processor 1234, etcetera.
Basically you use this instruction to copy the exception cause into a general purpose register and
this is used by the exception handling routine.
So essentially there needs to be support for this MFC-0 instruction.
Also, the goal is to move the cause into a general purpose register so that you can inspect it,
right?
Because you don't operate on these registers over here.
These are very special purpose.
This becomes general purpose.
And then there's also some other function.
I'll just read it over here.
I won't go into a lot of detail, but essentially in summary, an exception causes the processor to
jump to the exception handler.
We knew that the exception handler saves registers on the stack.
So there's some instructions that go through every single register.
Put it on memory so that you can return to it later on as we discussed.
Then uses MFC-0 to look at the cost and respond accordingly.
Basically use MFC-0 to move that cost into a general purpose register and check when the handler is
finished.
It restores the registers from the stack it knew, it knows where it wrote the registers and it
restores them back to the general purpose register file.
Copies the return address from EPC to K0 which is a register in MIPS.
So you basically take this EPC exception causing program counter, put it into a general purpose
register called K0, and then do a jump register to K0, meaning set the PC to the value in K0, which
is the exception causing register.
This is to make things more general purpose.
Otherwise you could have connected this EPC directly over here and that's why they think of this as
a Co processor, etcetera.
You don't need to know about that, but essentially this is how things are handled.
This is how what I described is implemented.
You can jump into an exception routine and you can jump out of an exception routine and you can
write an handler.
Makes sense, right?
There's no magic basically.
So who who provides the exception handlers?
It's basically there could be default exception handlers in the operating system.
Programmer may be able to write them also or overwrite them.
For interrupt handlers, it's usually the operating system that provides the interrupt handling
routines.
OK, so this was multi cycle.
Sounds good right?
Unfortunately, there are more complications this, so this was a multi cycle machine, sorry, multi
cycle data path with multi cycle execute as we learned there are more complications.
Basically instructions can take different number of cycles in the execute stage and this complicates
exception and drop handling.
Basically you cannot do exactly what I said, right?
Because now we don't do 1 instruction at a time.
We're actually doing multiple instructions concurrently at this point, right?
So how do we actually fix the problem?
We're writing to some registers out of order.
One way of fixing the problem is don't do that, right?
That's always the easiest way.
You banned that.
Unfortunately, bans don't necessarily work.
You could do this.
Basically make each operation take the same amount of time.
Divide takes 8 cycles, so I'll make add 8 take 8 cycles also so that I don't run into this problem.
Well, what if it load takes 500 cycles?
Well, I'll make add take 500 cycles also.
But if the load takes 2000 cycles, I'll make load to take 2000 cycle add to take 2000 cycles also.
So hopefully you get the point.
Worst case instruction latency determines all instructions latency.
And we know based on the design principles that this is not a good design, right?
You should not optimise for the worst case.
You should really optimise for the common case.
In this particular case, the worst case is actually terrible potential memory operations, as we
discussed.
Does each functional unit take the worst case number of cycles?
Unfortunately, that's not good.
Yeah, so that's why.
It's not a, it's a non solution to the problem.
So we're going to talk about solutions to the problem.
And all of these solutions that are written over here are implementing modern processors with some
combination history Buffer is depends on what kind of processor, but reorder buffer, feature
register file and checkpointing are all implemented.
I'm going to talk about the reorder buffer and I'm going to give you some examples of this, but this
paper actually covers this in a nice way.
And the Smith and Sohey paper that is a more overview paper covers in a more general way.
So basically, how do we support precise exceptions in the presence of instructions completing out of
out of program order?
I'll give you the concept of reorder buffer and leave these for you to study unless we have time,
which is very unlikely at the end.
But we have some lecture video from a long time ago that talks about these solutions that goes into
the details.
And also there are backup slides if you're interested.
But let me give you the idea of the reorder buffer.
Essentially, it's a very simple idea, although it will complicate our machine, unfortunately.
Idea is to complete the instructions are out of order, like this picture, but we're not going to
exact this picture, Complete it out of order.
Don't do this like bad design.
Do a good design, but reorder them before updating the register file, meaning before making the
results visible to the architectural state, right?
So that no one can see that you completed them out of order, right?
That's the idea.
Basically, That's a very simple idea, very powerful idea.
What we have here is at the end of the functional unit.
When the instruction finishes, it writes its results into the reorder buffer.
And when the instruction is the oldest instruction in the machine and it doesn't have exceptions and
there are no interrupts to be handled, it writes.
It takes its result from the reorder buffer and puts it into the register file.
So only when the instruction is the oldest instruction in the machine, the result moves from the
reorder buffer into the register file.
Register file is not written with values that are completed in an out of order way.
Register file is written with values that are completed in an in order manner.
That's the idea basically.
Let me quickly go over like what happens in a machine when an instruction is decoded, which is over
here, it reserves the next sequential entry in a special buffer called the reorder buffer.
So reorder buffer is a very special buffer.
It keeps track of the ordering of operations.
Every instruction goes through it when it's decoded, decoding has happened sequentially.
Remember, I fetched the instruction sequentially.
I decode it sequentially, right?
So it reserves the next sequential entry in a special buffer.
How to design this reorder buffer is going to be our challenge after the break, not after the longer
break.
After the short lecture break, you know OK, when an instruction completes, it writes its results
into the reorder buffer entry.
As I said, when an instruction is the oldest in the reorder buffer.
So you need to have a oldest instruction pointer to the reorder buffer as well as the youngest
instruction pointer.
But when the instruction is the oldest in the reorder buffer and it has completed without
exceptions, its result is moved to the register file or memory.
I'm not going to talk about memory here.
Memory makes things much more complicated, as we will see later on.
We're going to talk about registers still, but you still need to consider memory also, right?
Because you don't want to update memory out of order either.
If you have a store that comes later in the program, you don't want to update the memory because
that's hurts.
Again, all of these things, precise exceptions.
So this is a hardware structure that keeps information about all instructions that are decoded but
not yet retired or committed.
So it's really a circular buffer in hardware, circular queue.
You probably implemented circular queues in data structures or algorithms.
You can implement anything that you implement in software in hardware as well, except hardware
becomes a little bit more complicated.
So it's a circular queue.
There's an oldest instruction pointer pointer to the reorder buffer entry that contains information
about all this instructions in the machine.
There's a youngest instruction pointer that you allocate at the decode stage into OK, As I said,
it's a circular queue and hardware.
It has a lot of things that are inside it, and we're going to get to that after the break.
But whether the entry is valid, meaning whether there's an instruction in this ordering buffer
that's associated with it, What is this?
What is that instruction writing to destination register ID?
What is the value it has written if it has written that value at this point, because it may not have
written that value yet because there is a long execution pipeline or number of cycles, right?
That may happen.
So we're going to get to all of these in a little bit.
Let's, I think let's take a break.
There's a good picture to remember, I think.
Let's come back at, I hope that we can end the lecture early because I have a meeting at the end of
this.
So let's come back at 15.
15 when the bell rings and we're going to go over how this reorder buffer operates.
Just to jog your memory, this is the structure that we're looking at.
We're going to use the structure to reorder instructions, meaning it'll hold all the instructions
that are decoded but not yet retired.
The results may be here.
So every entry corresponds to a single instruction, and there's an ordering.
There's an old oldest pointer, and there's a youngest pointer, and each entry has a valid bit saying
whether an instruction has been assigned to that reorder buffer entry.
Each entry has a destination register ID if the instruction is writing to a register.
For instruction that writes to registers, each entry has a bit that says whether the destination
register is written to, meaning the instruction has completed and stored its value into the reorder
buffer.
And if that bit is set, then the value corresponding to that entry is the value that the instruction
has produced, and it will be written into the register file when the instruction becomes the
oldest, assuming there are no exceptions, etcetera.
Makes sense, right?
So that's the bare bones entry we have for keeping track of what happened to the instruction.
But that's not enough actually.
There needs to be more.
I will go through some.
This is a valid bit of the reorder buffer entry.
This is the destination register ID.
This is the destination register value.
If it's a store instruction, which we're not going to talk a lot about, you need a store address and
the data value that you're going to write, because if it's a store instruction, you don't want to
actually finish it out of order.
Also, you want to whenever the store instruction completes, it writes its address and data into the
reorder buffer entry.
And whenever it becomes the oldest instruction in the machine, if it doesn't cause any exceptions,
it basically takes that data value and writes it into the memory at that store address.
Hopefully that makes sense, right?
OK.
The program counter is also needed because this is a program counter of the instruction that was
written into the reorder bar for entry.
If there's an exception, you will need that program counter, right?
That will be your exception causing program counter, and that will be needed so that you can store
that and eventually return to the program if it's possible and desirable, right?
And this is the exception?
It's a bit, a single bit saying is there an exception?
And there should be something related to what kind of exception also, right?
So there's a lot of a lot of bookkeeping information that needs to be kept inside the reorder
buffer.
I don't actually individually enumerate these, but there should be valid bits for whether the
destination register is written to, whether the store address is written to, whether the store data
is written to, for example, and some other control bits like.
What kind of exception does this cost?
So you can think of this as a bookkeeping entry for a given instruction that's in the machine that's
decoded but not yet retired.
Now you have an order of these instructions, OK?
Basically, you need everything that's required to correctly reorder the instructions back into the
program order.
You kind of have that with the valid bits and also oldest instruction pointer and the youngest
instruction pointer, right?
Update the architectural state with the instructions result if the instruction can retire without
any issues.
That's why you have the register ID, store addresses, register values, store data, etcetera.
And also you need everything that you need that is required to handle an exception and interrupt
precisely if an exception or interrupt needs to be handled before retiring the instruction, right?
That's why you have this program counter exception?
And type of exception bits, you could have other things also.
We may expand this later on when we talk about out of order execution, but these are the basics.
So this actually could be a large structure in your machine.
As I said, you need valve bits to keep track of the readiness of the results and find out if the
instruction has complete the execution.
That's really important and we're going to use them soon.
So with every order buffer, this is the behaviour that we want from the machine.
When the instruction completes, the result is first written to the reorder buffer entry associated
with that instruction, and the result is taken from the reorder buffer.
And written to the register file only when that instruction is supposed to update the architectural
state in sequential order, right?
So what now?
Now we've coupled, we've decoupled writing it to the register file from producing the result and
writing it to the reorder buffer, right?
Every instruction, when it's completes, it writes its result into the register, sorry, reorder
buffer immediately.
And then there's some logic.
It's actually a small finite state machine that checks the reorder buffer and checks if the head of
the reorder buffer, meaning the oldest instruction reorder buffer is ready, meaning has written its
result and it hasn't caused any exception and there are no interrupts to handle at this point.
At that point, that finite state machine moves the result from the reorder buffer into the register
file and book updates the bookkeeping information such that the oldest instruction pointer moves to
the next instruction in the circular queue.
Hopefully that makes sense, right?
Basically, you need a separate finite state machine to manage what's going on in the reorder buffer.
But this fixes our problem.
Sounds good, right?
Beautiful.
We added, we threw more hardware at the problem to make sure the von Neumann model is satisfied.
Now, unfortunately, well, there are some other issues.
Basically, yes, we have put the result somewhere, but the question is what if a later instruction
needs a value that's in the reorder buffer?
In our example, everything was independent.
But what if this instruction, for example to execute needed the value of this instruction?
It's cannot get it from the register file because the register file is not written yet.
But the value is somewhere.
It's cannot get it from the bypass or forwarding pass because the previous instruction is done.
The value is there in the reorder buffer, right?
You can get it, but you need to do some more work to get that value and that's what we're going to
deal with right now.
And this is going to be really important for building auto board execution machines later on.
Hopefully that makes sense, right?
OK.
So one option is not get the value.
The value is present over here and you want to read it at this point, but it's not in the register
file, it's in the reorder buffer.
It's not in the bypass pass, etcetera.
Stall the pipeline.
And we've seen that that's a bad idea in the past, right?
Storing the pipeline, even though the values produced gets rid of a lot of the benefits of
pipelining, OK?
The better option is read the value from the reorder buffer because the value is there, you just
need to get it.
Now the problem becomes how do you get it?
OK.
So essentially how do we access the reorder buffer, right?
More generally, a register value that you're trying to read can be in the register file, can be in
the reorder buffer or can come from the bypass pass if the instruction is still in the pipeline
executing, right?
So all of these can happen.
And you saw you saw the Maxis to enable data coming from the register file versus the bypass pass.
Now we're going to add the reorder buffer also here as a potential place where the register value
that you need, source register value that you need can come from.
But this is going to complicate our life.
It's not as easy as the register file.
And we're going to talk about this because it's a very important concept in actually how to design
memories.
OK, so register file, we have seen this, you have some number of registers, R0 through R7, for
example, right in LC3R0 through R31 in MIPS.
This is called random access memory.
You index the register file with the register ID and that's your address, right?
We've seen we've built these memories before.
All of the memories that we've built so far are random access memories, right?
Relatively easy.
Register ID is the address of an entry.
Now, reorder buffer is a different kind of structure, right?
You want to read register 7, but reorder buffer is not organised that way.
How do you figure out where is register 7 in the reorder buffer, assuming that it's there?
Well, you need to search it basically, right?
You don't know whether it's there or not yet.
But you need to have a mechanism to index the reorder buffer somehow to get the value of register
seven that you're trying to read.
But you cannot index reorder buffer with just the address of the register register ID, right?
Because register 7 means nothing for the reorder buffer.
As I said, it's a circular buffer.
It has actually.
Let's go back to how it looks.
It has 16 entries.
Could be more than the number of registers, less than the number of registers.
Has nothing to do with the number of registers.
Entry ID has nothing to.
To do with the number of registers, right?
So the address random access address is nothing to do with the registers.
The register ID is actually inside the reorder buffer.
You can see that destination register ID.
There could be multiple instructions writing to register 7.
Let's say.
We will see that especially in the out of order execution lecture and you need to find which entry
is writing to register 7.
So in order to find out whether someone is writing to register 7 and whether that someone has
produced someone, meaning some instruction, whether that instruction has produced the value,
meaning that bit is set, you need to search the reorder buffer in a content addressable way.
So this is the notion of content reducible memory.
You essentially search every single entry with the ID of the register and ID of the register is part
of the content of the entry, right?
Does that make sense?
So that's the idea.
Basically, we're going to build a content addressable memory.
How many people have seen content addressable memories before?
OK, a few people, maybe less than a few.
That's good.
Now you're going to learn this is implementing essentially many, many processors.
It's an expensive type of memory and we're going to get rid of it.
But it's important for you to learn it first to understand why we want to get rid of it.
You cannot always get rid of it, but in this particular case, we're going to get rid of it.
But we're going to have a lot of content, addressable memories.
When we build an out of order execution machine, the same concept will come back.
OK, so we're going to do this example where we run a magical program.
So I'm going to use that in a little bit.
You have a register file.
I'm going to let me set up the stage over here.
You have a register file and you have a value associated with the register file, and you address the
register file with the register ID.
We're going to add a valid bit to the register file also saying that this value in the register is
correct and you can trust it and you can read it, meaning that is the real value that you want.
It's not going to be updated by someone else.
OK, reorder buffer.
We're going to look at anti valid, a destination register ID, destination register value and whether
the destination register has been written, right?
So we're going to execute some code with some assumptions.
We're going to do and we're going to see for example, how this how this multiply can look for a
value that's in the reorder buffer, right?
Can you switch?
Right now I don't have the animation.
If someone wants to do this animation, we can pay you to do a nice animation.
You have a better animation.
The out of order execution lecture.
But we forgot to do this one.
Although this is also nice.
I always say something different when I write this.
OK, before I guess maybe.
Yeah.
Is it good?
Oh, OK.
Can you guys see it?
Looks nice.
OK, so before I go through the example, I should say that.
So register ID, right?
Let's say register ID is 3.
You can see it, right?
If it's three, then you directly index using an address decoder and you get the value out.
That's easy.
Now, if our register ID is 3, how do you actually figure out whether register ID 3 exists in the
reorder buffer?
The hardware structure for this is not a decoder in a Max, which I'm not going to draw over here,
which was random access memory.
The hardware structure for this is you're going to take the destination register ID.
Basically, you're going to check whether destination register ID matches register ID 3.
It's an equality checker, whether they're equal.
And you've seen those equality checkers, right?
X NOR gates and for every entry you have an equality checker.
So register ID is input.
Let's assume it's three.
You check and then whether it's true or false, right?
And then another one true or false.
I could keep doing this forever and we can waste our nice lecture time true or false.
But you can see the complexity now, right?
So I'm going to do a few more times so that you can appreciate the complexity of this content
addressable memory...
dot dot you have 16 of these.
Let me do it for the next one.
Also, why not...
dot to be complete true or false?
OK, so basically you need to, this is the content of this full memory.
You're searching for a register ID and you need to check whether that register ID matches a register
ID that's stored in the structure.
So you need 16 comparators, equality checkers, actually comparators, that's actually the same thing.
And this comparator size grows with the number of entries you have.
Number of linearly grows with the number of entries you have.
Also grows the hardware complex grows with the idea of the destination register you have right now.
It's not that easy actually, as we will see in the execution of this program.
You don't want all the values, right?
What if there are, let's say, 4 entries that match register 3?
Which one do you want?
Clearly you don't want all the values that are written by all of the instruction.
You want the youngest instruction, meaning the instruction that wrote to register 3 just before you,
not the older ones.
So it's not just a search that looks like this, it's also an age based search.
You actually need to compare the ages, which I'm not going to draw over there, but it's actually a
more complicated search.
Not that.
Also you need to also keep track of the pointers, right?
You want only things that are here, right?
You don't care about things that are not inside the reorder buffer.
They may be values, but you don't want to match them, right?
So it's a content adjustable search that's age based that needs to be applied to all the
instructions that are between oldest and youngest in a circular queue.
This queue is circular, meaning at some point oldest may become this and the oldest, youngest may
stay here, for example, right?
And then the queue is not basically, this is the oldest instruction and these are the sequential
instructions that come after that, right?
So this is the complexity of the hardware, and we're going to get rid of that.
But let me go over this example a little bit to see what we do.
So initially, let me actually give more detail on why this matters.
So initially, all of the registers are valid.
Well, I started with the wrong value.
Let me fix it.
Redundancy helps.
Error correction, as you can see, right?
That's a very generic method for dependable.
OK, Register 0 is valid initially.
All of the registers are valid.
That's at the beginning of the program.
Reorder buffer is empty, meaning all the Stein youngest instruction pointers are the same.
Let's do that.
Why not?
Right?
And there's nothing in the reorder buffer.
And all of these are 0000.
I'm not going to write the zeros over there.
If you have other pins, that could be useful also at some point.
Yeah, we do have other pins.
And let's assume that register file looks like the 0123.
These are the values 4I cannot write six.
Hopefully AI can write for me at some point.
OK, so basically let's assume that we're fetched and we're decoding this instruction, Multiply R1R
2R3 decode process.
What it does is it reads the source registers, right?
What do you do?
So one source registers R1R1 is valid.
So the value here is good.
So multiply is sourcing one that's good.
So this will be 1.
Multiply reads the register.
It's going to multiply later on.
It checks this one R2 is valid also, that's good, and reads 2.
The value over there is 2, so this is 2.
So multiply can execute because its values are ready.
But we're not done yet.
We just fetched and decoded multiply.
We got the source registers.
We need to deal with the destination register and also the reorder buffer, right destination
register.
Now multiply did not produce its result yet.
So what it does at the decode stage is it sets the valid bit of the R3, which is destination
register to 0, meaning I'm going to write to this value.
So it's not going to be 3 anymore, or you'll be lucky if it's three anymore and it's not going to be
3 based on these numbers.
Basically, I'm not going to it's not going to be 3 anymore.
Don't trust this result.
This result is going to be somewhere else.
OK And Multiply also allocates A reorder buffer entry entry 0.
On this particular case, it sets the entry 0 valve bit.
It sets destination register ID to three destination register value.
We don't know yet.
Destination register is not written yet.
Zero.
OK.
And then there are some other things over there.
And then youngest instruction pointer is incremented so that the next instructor gets allocated to
the next location.
OK, So that's what happens in the decode stage for this multiply sounds good right?
Now this is OK, interesting.
But what happens here is more interesting.
So the second multiply the source registers R3.
The source register is R3RT is not trusted, right?
So R3 is not here.
So I cannot trust this three value.
So what do I do with that?
Let's ignore that.
Let's do the R4R4 is easy.
R4 is trusted over here.
So I get the value 4 over here.
Right now R3 is not here and it's not in the bypass path.
Let's say this.
This multiply needs to search the reorder buffer.
And let's assume for the sake of this that at some point I'll have a better example that there's a
huge distance between them.
This multiply may have produced its result for example OK.
I'm going to violate something, but it's OK, I guess.
This multiply gets allocated to this entry over here.
The second one, it's writing to R11.
The value is not ready yet.
Yeah.
And you increment the youngest instruction counter now to check whether R3 is in the reorder buffer.
This R3 gets searched everywhere, right?
With the structure that I built over here that I'm not going to be able to get.
So this R3 gets input and every entry is searched.
And guess what?
You get a match in entry 0, right?
This becomes true.
This is your own entry, so you can search for it fine, but you don't get a match.
You should not get a match because it should be the older instruction and you should discard
whatever results are coming from the comparators over here because all of these entries have 0 eval
bits over here, right?
So this multiply should get its results from this entry when it's produced, but it's not produced
yet.
OK, because it's not produced yet, this multiply is going to stall the pipeline.
Now, in the next lecture, you will see methods where this multiply is going to be moved somewhere.
It's going to wait over there for out of order execution, and then the next add will come.
Let's assume that it's there.
Fine.
The purpose is to demonstrate the reorder buffer right now.
Oh, we forgot something really important with this multiply.
It sets our 11, well bits to 0, right?
And basically this 11 is kind of useless at that point.
OK, so when you decode the instruction, you set the valve between the register file 0A register file
for the destination register zero, you allocate an entry in the reorder buffer and basically you
set up the reorder buffer with the destination register ID, etcetera.
OK, now this add R5 and R6R3.
Let's take a look at it because there's something interesting that's going to happen over here.
What should I use?
Purple.
Why not?
This add is purple.
I don't know why I used a green for the other multiplies.
Why should I use different colours?
OK, this add R5R6R5 is valid.
That's good.
R6 is valid.
So it's going to add 5 + 6.
That's good.
It's going to write to R3R3.
It's not going to read.
It's already invalid.
So it keeps the invalid bit over there as you, but it's going to go into entry two over here.
It's going to write to R3 again.
OK, And then you're going to increment the youngest instruction pointer.
OK, now you know, you see why you get multiple R threes over here, right?
This other ad.
OK, let's do.
Let's do that ad also.
OK, I forgot something with the don't forget, don't ever forget updating that.
Oh, we did.
We did update, so it's also zero.
OK, so now this next ad comes, this next ad is doing something interesting.
For the purpose of this example, it's reading from R3, right?
Let's ignore that for now.
It's reads from R8, so R8 is easy.
What's going on with these pencils, pens.
Maybe we're stuck with the green one, I guess.
OK, you need to push them a bit.
OK, 18 so this reads 8R12, it's going to write to R12.
It sets the valid of R12 to 0.
Hopefully you can see it.
And when it reads R3, it knows that R3 is not valid over here.
This is not trustworthy.
But now it needs to do search again, right?
And what is that search?
That search will need to again go back over here.
Maybe I'll replicate this over here like this is 3, this is 3, this is 11.
Basically, both of these will match, but you should get the result that's going to be written over
here, right?
Not this result, meaning this instruction should get the value produced by this ad and not this
multiply.
So we have an interesting thing over here, which is by searching the reorder buffer, you can figure
out which instruction produced your result because we have enough information in the reorder
buffer, right?
This is, this is called really tag search and we will see that even more detail later on.
Yes, in the version where it just installed, Yes.
How do you wake up the the right one?
How do you wake up which is which?
Which one is the right one?
What's the first one?
Yeah, we're going to talk about that next lecture.
Yes.
I just want to show the operation of how you search in the reorder buffer right now.
Wake up will come after the break.
There will be specialised logic for that.
And we're going to complete the whole picture.
Very good question basically, yes, very good.
So you have, you have a very good point basically whether an instruction we're going to fix that
problem also keep that for now.
So I didn't really build the full picture.
The goal was to really show the I'm going to fix that problem in a little bit.
OK, bear with me.
But very good, you have identified something.
Basically, if this instruction now finishes, it should not write this value over here because that
would not be the correct value.
OK, OK, very good.
You guys are thinking.
I like it.
So the purpose of this example was to demonstrate that when you actually decode the instructions you
need to read from the register file and the valid values, you can get invalid values.
You have to consult something else, right?
But when the reorder buffer finishes, there should be something else over here that decides whether
or not you write, and we're going to see that in a little bit.
OK, that sounds good.
OK, we're going to, we're going to fix that right away.
OK, go ahead.
Yeah, OK, forget about that for now.
We're going to get to that.
But yes, it could lengthen your clock cycle, all of these operations, but you could also break it
into multiple stages.
So all of the decodes can happen in one clock cycle depending on your clock cycle.
Yeah, we're going to talk about performance analysis later on a little bit more.
Good questions.
OK, maybe you can switch right now.
I'm going to fix the problem that you mentioned, and also I'm going to get rid of this content
addressable memory.
Maybe.
OK, maybe, I guess she switched already.
OK, maybe, maybe I'll handle it in the other one.
I'll handle it in the other one.
Go ahead.
I wanted to introduce concept, but let's fix the problem that you have because it's going to bug
you.
You're going to switch again, so maybe you can stay here.
OK, so we handled this so simplifying reorder buffer access.
The the problem is reorder buffer access is very complicated, right?
How do we simplify this access?
We want to turn from a content addressable memory to random access memory for the purpose of
accessing registers.
How do we do that?
Well, using direction basically a lot of problems can in in computing can be solved within
direction.
If you remember that quote, the idea is to access the register file first, check if the register is
valid and then access reorder buffer Next, don't do it concurrently.
Right now reorder buffer does not need to be content reducible, but you need to add some metadata.
That metadata is essentially what we will call A tag.
If the register is not valid, the register file stores the ID of the reorder buffer entry that
contains or that will contain the value of the register.
So that's called the tag or reorder buffer entry ID.
This is going to solve your problem because now the tag contains the reorder buffer entry ID that's
going to write to the register, and only that reorder buffer entry ID will write to that register.
No one else can write to that register, even if it's the oldest.
And if it's, there's no exceptions.
Solved your problem.
OK, good.
So this also introduces something that's really fundamental and important.
Now we're really mapping the register to a reorder buffer entry.
This enables a lot of optimisations that we're going to see in out of order execution and this is a
powerful concept.
Register file maps to register to a reorder buffer entry if there's an in flight instruction writing
to that register.
Now remember ISA lectures we had limited number of registers, right?
I have only three bits, 4 encoding registers in LC3.
I have only 5 in MIPS.
This limits the locality that we can exploit in the register file.
Now if I have a bigger structure that I can design, which is reorder buffer that contains all of the
values, that's why I can make it.
And the reason, one of the reasons why we cannot increase the register file size is the encoding,
right?
If you actually have 1000 registers, for example, you need 10 bits to encode those registers, right?
1024 and 10 bit, 10 bit, 10 bit.
You have a 30 bit encoding for registers just for registers in your instruction encoding.
Here, what we're doing is we we can build a larger structure called reorder buffer that can have
thousands of registers in existing architectures.
It's actually 5500 or 1500, somewhere in between.
And you can have a very small architectural register file, 8 of them.
But you can actually keep pointing to new definitions of the registers, right?
OK, this is going to become more clear.
OK, this is called register renaming.
Basically, we're going to rename the register to the reorder buffer entry.
OK, now it's your turn.
We're going to do the, I guess, same example with the tag, right?
Now we're going to go more quickly, I guess, because now you're familiar with what's going on.
OK, so it's the same example, but now let's do, let's execute this.
Multiply R1R 2R3.
I guess I'll populate these again.
And initially there's 01234567 and then there's A tag.
These tags, we don't care initially because they're all valid.
OK, so multiply R1R 2R3.
I read the source entries, R1 is ready.
The value is to be trusted.
So that's going to be two.
Oh, did that happen?
No, there's going to be 1.
Sorry, I, I looked at the wrong 1R2 is ready.
The value is trusted.
So we're going to multiply 1 and 2.
We're going to write the result into R3.
So I'm going to allocate an entry in the reorder buffer for this multiply.
It's going to write into R3 register three.
We don't know the value.
It's not ready yet.
And I'm going to point make R3 invalid because the value in the register file is not correct
anymore.
It's going to be updated by what's whatever is produced by this multiply.
And I'm going to put as tag.
Let's to be very clear, I guess Rob 0 reorder buffer entry 0.
Now this is a pointer to this entry zero saying that R3 is going to be produced.
R3 is not valid.
Don't trust this value.
R3 is going to be produced by reorder buffer entry 0.
So whenever that we order buffer entry zero, produce it, get it.
We're going to talk about how that's getting it will happen later on.
But now what we've done is we've eliminated the content address for search over here, right?
So let's take a look at what happens to this other multiply that's going to read R3R4.
Let's read R4R4 is easy.
As we've discussed, it gets 4R3.
Now this multiply knows directly that R3 will come from ROB 0 just by accessing the register file,
right?
So this is going to come from ROB 0 reorderable for entry zero.
And R11 right now will be invalid.
Oh, that's a big R11.
This is not trusted and we have a OK to make it easier to read.
I'm going to make this ROB one because it's going to be allocated ROB one right now what whoever
sources R11 will get the value from Rob one right?
And it doesn't need to do a counter intensivable search here at least.
OK, let's take a look at the other R3 because it's going to make it more interesting right now.
It's going to solve your problem.
Also, as we discussed R5R6, these are easy fives and six.
Well, it's basically this is ready.
R3 is 0 this when this arc ad gets decoded, the tag gets changed to rob 2 because this add is
allocated an entry in reorder buffer entry 2 makes sense right?
So what happened was there is a new definition of R3R3 was defined by this multiply and it's value
was pointed to buy to rob zero.
And every instruction that came after this multiply knows that the value is going to come from
reorder buffer entry 0.
So we kind of linked this definition of R3 to all of the instructions that are sourcing it.
Later someone else wrote into R3 change that definition to reorder buffer NT 1.
So every instruction that comes after this AD will look at reorder buffer NT1.
No, sorry, reorder buffer entry two.
Yeah, I should say 2.
So every instruction that comes after this at we'll look at reorder buffer entry 2.
Now, if there's another definition of R3 at some point, let's assume that this is R3 somehow, it's
not here.
Of course, that instruction will change the pointer, meaning the tag to that entry number 34, in
this case 5 for up five.
Basically what we're doing is we're really renaming the register ID to the reorder buffer entry ID.
Such that later instructions that source that particular value of the register is going to source
the right place, get the value from the right place.
This is called register renaming, and we accomplished multiple things by adding this tag over here,
actually renaming what's happening in the older version also, but here we're more explicit right
now.
Basically we're renaming register 3 to wrap zero, and when that register 3 gets written again at the
decode stage, an instruction is going to write to register 3 again.
It gets renamed to whatever reorder bar for entry.
It's going to be allocated OK, And we know exactly where to look for no content addressable memory,
read it anymore.
Makes sense, right?
Yes.
And previous instructions we'll use then the text from previous times.
Exactly.
Yes, exactly.
Yes.
I haven't connected the final thing yet because we're going to do that in the lecture in out of
order execution because there needs to be also a mechanism to actually get the value when it's
available, like waking up instructions.
But hold that off for now.
We are still reordering instructions, but I'm extending the concept.
The reorder buffer concept is actually more powerful than just reordering instructions, right?
It's also enabling us to actually map a register to many other potential places in the register.
And these R3's have nothing to do with each other.
Remember in the last lecture, we, this is a right to R3, This is another right.
This is a right after right dependence.
It's a force dependence, right?
And we said that we can eliminate force dependence.
This is how we eliminate force dependences.
These R3, the 1st R3 is here.
The 2nd R3 is here.
The second definition of R3, the third definition is here.
And there could be other definitions of R3 by other instructions.
Right?
Right to R3.
Basically these R3's have nothing to do with each other.
The reason this instruction is right to R3 and this other instruction also writes to R3 is because
we don't have enough registers in the ISA.
If we had enough registers, there's no reason to reuse the registers in the ISA.
And the fact that we have enabled created a lot of space over here for more registers that are not
visible to the ISA, enabled us to actually have those registers without informing the programmer or
the software.
And that's the beauty of it.
This is the beauty of the micro architecture.
In the micro architecture, we can have a lot of registers even though the architecture limits us.
OK, maybe we can switch.
Thanks.
Any questions while switching happens?
Context switch overhead.
So many, like you said, 1500.
And yeah, you'll see in the next lecture, because you want to have a lot of instructions to tolerate
latencies in the machine.
If your memory latency is like 500 cycles and if you have one instruction that's waiting for memory
at the top, if you don't want to stall the machine, you want to keep fetching instructions.
You need to have actually lots of entries in the machine.
Some of them may be completed, some of them may be still executing, some of them may be waiting.
Yes, exactly.
Overall, yes.
But we're going to be more careful in that definition soon.
OK, so these things are implemented in real life.
Pentium 3 which was the first out of order machine which we will see later on had essentially this
is the register file, although everything is a pointer over here.
So they went to the next step which out which we will discuss in the next lecture.
Register is called the register alias table.
There they have 8 registers in X86 and everything is a pointer.
Some pointers go to the reorder buffer, some pointers go to the actual register file.
So they've they've gone one more step than what I have done over here.
If you can see this, instead of having these over here, they remove the valve bits.
They put these somewhere over here and all they have is the tax.
Basically when an instruction comes, it checks where where it's value is at.
It could be in the reorder buffer, it could be in the register file, right?
So all you need is pointers basically.
You don't even need a valve bit.
It's beautiful, right?
OK.
And we're going to talk more about that later on.
And this is Intel Pentium Pro.
It was the most successful out of order machine.
First out of order machine.
Let's say it's not the first, it's the most successful first.
OK, So basically what we've done is eliminated output and anti dependence.
And we discussed that they're not true depends.
So I have shown you output dependence, but anti dependence, they're also eliminated this way because
you're actually you're actually not bothered by them anymore.
These, the same registry refers to values that have nothing to do with each other.
These exist due to lack of register IDs in the ISA.
Now what we've done is that we renamed the register to the reorder buffer entry that will hold the
register's value.
Register ID gets mapped to reorder buffer.
For entry, we will later change this to architectural register ID gets mapped to physical register
ID.
So we're going to actually expand this concept and after renaming, we order buffer entry ID is used
to refer to the register and this is going to be how we communicate values inside an out of order
machine.
Whenever we talk about the register, we're not going to talk about the architectural register
number.
We're going to talk about the physical register ID or tag associated with it.
And instructions get linked to each other because one instruction that reads the tag from the
register file, just like we did, knows that if someone actually produces that tag and sends it to
you, this is A tag I'm looking for because that's the tag I'm waiting for, right?
So that's how instructions will get linked to each other.
OK.
This will eliminate anti and output dependences completely.
We don't need to worry about them, which is beautiful.
We don't change the ISA and it gives the illusion that there are actually a lot of registers and the
illusion is actually real because there's, these are called physical registers in the reorder
buffer.
These are the values of the registers.
You may have 1500 R threes over here if your program actually writes to R3 all the time for whatever
reason.
Not a good program probably, but it's possible, you know, OK, so remember these are the flow
dependences.
This is anti dependence.
So this does not become a problem anymore.
This does not become a problem anymore.
The only issue is really true dependences right now.
So we still need to maintain true dependences.
But by assigning A tag to this R3 and by assigning by enabling the instruction that sources that tag
that that sources this version of R3.
To get that tag, you can link the instruction that produces that version of R3 to the instruction
that consumes that version of R3.
OK, so this is going to be on your own, I think, because we don't have a lot of time.
But essentially this is something to do where you look at the latest definition of R3 for each
instruction below in sequential order.
We're going to do more of these after the break, and you can simulate this yourself if you want.
It's going to be fun.
Let me conclude the INGO order pipeline with the order buffer.
So in order pipeline means you have in order dispatch and in order execution dispatch means here
you're dispatching things in order.
You do out of order completion of operations and in order retirements.
And this was our reorder buffer.
Reorder buffer is implemented as a circular queuing hardware.
So whenever you're decoding, you also access the reorder buffer, right, either sequentially or
concurrently with the register file.
So on decode, we access the register file and reorder buffer, allocate entry in the reorder buffer,
check if the instruction can execute.
If so, we can dispatch the instruction on execute instructions can complete out of order completion.
Rewrite the results into the reorder buffer retirements.
We already discussed all of these, but check all this instruction for exceptions.
If no exceptions, write the results into the architecture register file or memory assuming tag
matches remember.
Otherwise, flush the pipeline and start from the exception handler.
OK, so their advance and disadvance to reorder buffer.
Conceptually this is really simple, but you can see that the implementation has become very complex,
but it's going to enable us to do other stuff.
It can eliminate false dependency, so it enables renaming of registers, gives the illusion of a lot
of registers as we will see next time.
Also, the disadvantage is reorder buffer needs to be accessed to get the results that are yet to be
written into the register file.
This requires either a content addressable memory, which we didn't want, or some sort of
indirection.
Either way, it's going to increase our latency, complexity or both, right?
So indirection also increase our latency rate and also complexity, but not as bad as content
addressable memory.
So there are other solutions to this problem which I'm not going to cover.
As I said, history buffer, future file checkpointing, we're going to cover the future file kind of
when we talk about out of order execution because modern processors actually use a combination of
future file checkpointing and reorder buffer to actually handle this complicated state maintenance
issues to maximise performance.
But if you're interested, you can take a look at these lectures or ask questions.
So these are some interesting readings.
This is a reading that I suggest, but these precise interrupts in pipeline processors, it's a
Seminole paper that talks about how to do all of these actually.
And then checkpointing was introduced in this paper for out of order execution machines.
These may be better to read when you actually learn about out of order execution after the break.
That brings us to the end.
Any burning questions?
Guess not.
OK, have a great break.
I'll see you all after the break then hopefully you'll come refreshed.